Abdul Rehman

Intelligent Systems Engineering, Indiana University Bloomington 700 N Woodlawn Ave Bloomington, IN - 47408

■ 8127784435 | ■ abrehman@iu.edu | 😭 abrehman94.github.io | 🖸 github.com/abrehman94

Summary.

Ph.D. student with 8+ years of systems software development (6 years of full time industrial position) and systems research (2 years) experience. During my time in industry I have worked on UEFI firmware, Nucleus RTOS and NVMe virtualization. For past two years, my focus has been on serverless computing, linux scheduling and machine learning. I have added Rust, eBPF and deep learning approach using pyTorch to my toolbox. I am working under the guidance of Prateek Sharma at Indiana University Bloomington. I enjoy diving deep into complex problems, trying to find the last ounce of performance boost in myraid of interconnected components.

Education

Indiana University Bloomington

Bloomington, United States

Aug 2022 - Present

PhD in Intelligent Systems Engineering

Advisor: Prateek Sharma

- · Research area: cloud computing
- · CGPA 3.91/4.00
- Courses: Applied Algorithms, Cloud Computing, Compilers, Operating Systems, Deep Learning, Signal Processing using Machine Learning

Research Assistant Aug 2022 - Present

- · Current Research: Targeted Scheduling for a serverless platform (Linux, eBPF, SchedExt, Rust)
- Development of Realtime Data Analytics System using MQTT, InfluxDB and Torch Serve (see projects).
- Contributed to the development of a serveless platform written in Rust ground up (publication).

National University of Sciences and Technology

Islamabad, Pakistan

Electrical Engineering

Aug 2011 - June 2015

- CGPA 3.92/4.00
- Courses: Embedded Systems, Digital System Design, Digital Signal Processing

Publications

PUBLISHED

[1] Alexander Fuerst, **Abdul Rehman**, Prateek Sharma. Ilúvatar: A Fast Control Plane for Serverless Computing. *High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing(HPDC)* '23, Acceptance Rate 21%

UNDER PREPARATION

[1] **Abdul Rehman**, Prateek Sharma. λ Sched: A fine grained scheduling solution for an Energy Efficient Serverless Platform. *pending*, submission

Teaching Experience _____

Indiana University Bloomington

Bloomington, IN, United States

22nd Jul 2021 - 25th Jul 2021

- Luddy Summer School 2024
 Created a tutorial that introduces high school students to Ubuntu 20.04 and teaches basic bash scripting.
- Project Page: https://abrehman94.github.io/posts/luddy_summer_school.html

Work Experience _____

Siemens Industry Software Inc.

Mobile, AL, United States

Senior Software Engineer - Hypervisor Team

Mar 2021 - Sep 2021

- Siemens Hypervisor support on Intel Embedded Processors Elkhartlake (2021).
 - Release critical bug-fixes: ACPI parser, AHCI Virtualization, NVMe Virtualization
 - Mentoring a new engineer.

OCTOBER 8, 2024

Senior Software Engineer - Hypervisor Team

- · Feature Release: virtualized UEFI interface
 - Design and development of a non-volatile variable caching infrastructure to avoid SMI generation and provide real time gurantees for Guest RTOS.
- · Feature Release: NVMe Virtualization
 - Performance improvement of NVMe virtualization infrastructure from 700 MB/s to 1.5 GB/s. Improved the infrastructure to process requests across SMP cores.
 - Led a team of two engineers to deliver the project.

Software Engineer - Hypervisor Team

Aug 2016 - Jan 2020

- · Feature Release: virtualized UEFI interface
 - Implementation of UEFI boot support for Guest OS (Windows, Linux, RTOS) on Siemens Type 1 Hypervisor.
 - Design and development of a UEFI driver for Intel Graphics Device (IGD) to allow early graphics for Linux and Windows guests.
- Feature Release: NVMe Virtualization
 - Design and development of the infrastructure. Specifically, interrupt handling (PCI MSI-X capability) and I/O queue segregation for the
 virtual devices and hardware backend.
- Adapting the Linux NVMe driver to act as a Paravirtualized Client for testing purpose.
- Feature Releases for Mentor Embedded Hypervisor (Type 1)
 - Design and development of VT-d DMAR/IOMMU driver to allow device isolation and memory remapping of guests.

Software Engineer - Embedded UI Graphics Team

Jun 2015 - Aug 2016

- Feature Release: Qt GUI Framework version 5.4 on Nucleus RTOS
 - Porting of the framework based on a previous work for Qt 4.0.
 - Performance optimization of the ported framework.

Projects

Targeted CPU Scheduling for a serverless platform

Indiana University Bloomington

Mar 2024 - Present

- A custom CPU scheduling solution (using SchedExt framework) that uses function metadata to improve the performance of the serverless
 platform.
- Project Page: https://abrehman94.github.io/projects/schedext_based_scheduling.html

Edge-IoT-Analytics-Box - Extensible Data Analytics System

Indiana University Bloomington

Dec 2023 - May 2024

- A data analytics system that can be deployed on edge devices (protyped on Jetson Orin) to perform real-time data analytics.
- Project Page: https://abrehman94.github.io/projects/dataanalytics.html

Iluvatar a Serverless Control Plane in Rust

Indiana University Bloomington

Aug 2022 - May 2023

- A radical approach to serverless computing monolithic, worker centric platform.
- Project Page: https://abrehman94.github.io/projects/iluvatar.html

Awards

2023 **Travel Grant**, High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing 2023

Orlando, USA

Appreciation Certificates: exceptional debugging skills, high quality work, Mentor a Siemens Business

Lahore, Pakistan

Skills

Programming Languages Rust, C/C++, Bash, Python (Pandas, NumPy)

Application Level Distributed Systems (serverless, InfluxDB), Containerization(Docker, containerd)

Close to hardware eBPF, Linux Kernel, Type 1 Hypervisors (ACRN/XEN/MEHV/Siemens), UEFI Driver, ACPI, x86, Lauterbach Trace-32 Debuggers

Machine Learning PyTorch, Application of Deep Learning approach

Tools tmux, vim, ssh, perfetto

OCTOBER 8, 2024 2